An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society 1799-1882 Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
- Calendar of Letters
  - To Charles LYELL; Down (type 3), [1853] June 7th [end. June 1853; pmk. JU 9]; 107; ALS; 10 x8; 3p. and add. [Sir Charles Lyell/ Commissioner to the/ Great Exhibition/ New York/ U.S.], end. [15/ C. Darwin/ June 1853/ Weald Denudation]
    Thanks for two pamphlets, one of them "most useful"; attended June 1 meeting of Geological Society of London, describes proceedings; mentions [Peter C.] Sutherland's paper on ice-action, 1 [Joshua] Trimmer's paper; 2 [Roderick Impey] Murchison forwarded catastrophic cause of flints, so CD advanced Lyell's theory of sub-glacial action; Sutherland "most strongly" confirmed Lyell's belief that stones on the beaches in [France and England? the arctic countries?] were angular; [William] Hopkins accepted CD's theory of straight course cut through irregular terrain by highly plastic iceberge; [Robert] Chamber's "interesting" paper on glaciation 3 reproduces [Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz's idea of hemispheric ice-sheet and "treats all Icebergians with the most supercilious contempt."; missed "battle royal" at [annual election meeting] of Royal Society of London, but Murchison and [Francis] Beaufort "gained the day", and [Edward Augustus] Inglefield was elected, exceeding by one the allowed number of admissions; wife is visiting a sister; leaves on July 1 for a month at Isle of Wight, 4 after which CD will "go to press with my weariful cirripedes [Darwin, Recent Balanidae]."
    1. "On the Geological and Glacial Phaenomena of the Coasts of Davis' Strait and Baffin's Bay," Q. Jl. geol. Soc. Lond., 9 (1853), 296-312. The portion of the letter that comments on Sutherland is printed faithfully in Life and Letters I, 329, next to last paragraph.
    2. "On the Southern Termination of the Erratic Tertiaries,..." Q. Jl. geol. Soc. Lond., 9 (1853), 282-86; and "On the Origin of the Soils which Cover the Chalk of Kent, Part 3," ibid., 286-96.
    3. "On the Glacial Phenomena in Scotland and Some Parts of England," Edinb. new phil. J., 54 (1853), 229-82.
    4. The Darwins left instead for Eastbourne, Brighton, and Hastings on July 14; see "Darwin's Journal," 13.
  - To Charles LYELL; Down (type 3), [1854] Feb 18th. [pmk. FE19/ 1854]; 108; ALS; 10 x8; 4p., add. [Sir Charles Lyell/ care of H. Murray Esqr/ British Consul/ Santa Cruz/ Teneriffe/ Canary Islands], end. [C. Darwin/ sent to Madeira/ steeper dip of lateral volcc. geoly. than of/ central beds]
    Printed in full, with minor changes: Life and Letters I, 390-92. p. 391, line 1, change "Searle[?]" to "Seale". 1
    1. See Robert F. Seale, The Geognosy of the Island of St. Helena... (London: Ackermann & Co., 1834). Lyell mentions this book in his Elements of Geology, 2nd ed., 2v. (London: John Murray, 1841), II, 227.
  - To [John Stevens] HENSLOW; Down (type 3), [1854] Nov. 17th. [wmk. 1853]; 109; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Printed in full, with minor changes: Nora Barlow, ed., Darwin and Henslow: The Growth of an Idea (London: John Murray, 1967), 172 (letter 78).
  - To Charles LYELL; Down (type 3), [1855] Jany 10th [end. Jany 11, 1855; pmk. JA 10/ 55; wmk. 1849]; 110; ALS; 10 x8; 3p. and add. [Sir Charles Lyell/ 53 Harley St/ London], end. [(19) Ch. Darwin/ foliation of gneiss/ Jany 11,/ 1855.]
    Printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: More Letters, II, 204-05 (letter 540). At end of letter is: has found [Daniel] Sharpe's paper ["On the Structure of Mont Blanc and Its Environs," Q. Jl. geol. Soc. Lond., 11 (1855); 11-26]; children are recovering; will take a house in London for four weeks.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 3), [1855] Jan 14th [wmk. 1949]; 111; ALS; 10 x8; 4p. and sketch
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, II, 205-07 (letter 541). Sketch printed at end of printed letter.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 27 York Place, Baker St 1, [1855 January 21 or 28, or February 4 or 11] Sunday [wmk. 1853]; 112; ALS; 8 x5; 8p., sketch
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, II, 207-09 (letter 542). Sketch printed in middle of page 208. p. 209, line 10, add: "(Do read this P.S.)".
    1. The Darwins were at this address from January 18 to February 15; see "Darwin's Journal," 14.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down., [1855] May 8th; 113; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, II, 153-54 (letter 502).
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 3), [1855] Oct. 25th; 114; ALS; 7 3/4 x4 3/4; 3p.
    Crayford is too far away for CD to know anything about "Mrs. Shaw"; glad Eyton is thinking of dogs, an "excellent continuation of your capital Pig-Skeleton researches"; 1 impressed by Eyton museum [see DNB, XVIII, 107]; family details; recalls hobby of beetle collecting as a youth.
    1. Eyton, "Some Osteological Peculiarities in Different Skeletons of the Genus Sus," Proc. zool. Soc. Lond., 5 (1837): 23.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1855] Nov 4th; 115; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Returns two pamphlets 1 by [John] Bachman; surprised at their poor quality and at Bachman's unsubstantiated assertions, but, as [William Henry] Fitton said of [William] Whewell, " `one must make allowance for him [ sic] having sworn to what he believes in' "; "It is most useful to see what is said on all sides" and to read "out-of-the-way pamphlets of this nature"; has living pairs of seven or eight kinds of pigeon which shall be observed and then skeletonized; has begun "to cultivate varieties of plants & make hybrids, so that I have entered on my subject in earnest"; invites Lyells to Down to see pigeons; J[ohn William] Lubbock [first Baron Avebury] sent [Joseph Dalton] Hooker's New Zealand Flora 2 with [Thomas Vernon] Wollaston; please care for these volumes and return them sometime.
    1. Most likely these were: Continuation of the Review of `Nott and Gliddon's Types of Mankind' (Charleston: James, Williams & Gitsinger, 1855); and An Examination of the Characteristics of Genera and Species as Applicable to the Doctrine of the Unity of the Human Race (Charleston: James, Williams & Gitsinger, 1855). See Br. Mus. Cat., IX, 704; see also Cat. scient. Pap., I, 145-46, and VI, 573.
    2. The Botany of the Antarctic Voyage of H.M. Discovery-Ships Erebus and Terror in the Years 1839-1843..., Pt. II: Flora Novae-Zelandiae, 2v. (London: Lovell Reeve, 1853-1855).
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 2), [1855] Dec. 3d.; 116; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Thanks for useful information; is "well in[to] my subject"; has several pigeons in water, plus many alive, and means to get domestic pigeons from all parts of world; delighted that Eyton is at dogs, which will help both CD and "Science"; offers to Eyton the head of a Chinese dog and, if it should die, the carcass of a young, very pure bred German Spitz dog.
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 2), [1855] Dec 9th; 117; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Cannot find dog's head [see preceding letter, above]; thought Eyton had stopped skeletonizing, until Eyton told CD otherwise at [B.A.A.S.] meeting at Glascow [in September, 1855]; "I took to the nice work [skeletonizing of pigeons], first owing to my wish to see how much the young of Pigeons & Poultry differed from the old, & I have a collection in Brine of nestling Pigeons & chickens."; will not do more than give differences in skeletons of pigeons, poultry, covey birds, and rabbits; thanks for offer to lend pigeon skeletons (including "Almond Tumbler"); will not publish "for some years"; [William] Yarrell has done much bone work, has recently showed CD "a lot of breastbones"; CD's practice of buying curious pigeon carcasses from dealers could be used by Eyton for dogs; "A Mr [William Bernhard] Tegetmeier" will publish on skulls of Fowls, 1 recently showed CD a collection and "gave me a small series."
    1. "On the Remarkable Peculiarities in the Skulls of the Feather-crested Variety of the Domestic Fowl, Known as the Polish," Proc. zool. Soc. Lond., 24 (1856), 366-68. Read on November 25, 1856; specimens from Eyton's collection were exhibited at that meeting.
  - To [George Henry Kendrick THWAITES]; Down (type 2), 1855 Dec. 10; 118; ALS; 8 x5; 6p.
    Hopes Thwaites remembers CD from B.A.A.S. meeting at Oxford [1847]; for years, has collected for, and is now preparing, a work on variation of species; wants observations on "any changes in any introduced or feral plants or animals", esp. domesticated pigeons, poultry, ducks, and rabbits; wants all kinds alive, skeletons when dead; is trying especially to get live pigeons from all over world; wants names of pigeon fanciers in Ceylon; wants native names and any remarkable habits of pigeon breeds long kept in Ceylon or imported from anywhere except England; pay a bird skinner ten or fifteen shillings to skin (leaving bones of legs and wings) any old birds of any fancier which happen to die naturally; wants skins of poultry (except silk or black-skinned) or of domestic Ceylonese ducks, if there be any; wants any well-known fancy breed of pigeon (esp. "semi-wild Dove-House Pigeon") if it has been kept in Ceylon for many generations; there are many such in India; apologies for imposition; solicitations over health; "our mutual friend J[oseph Dalton] Hooker" is well.
  - Autographs of Members of "Philosophical Club of Royal Society", 1855 Decr. 20th [wmk. 1855]; 119; DS; approx. 13 x8; 2p.
    Signatures on one side, minutes of the meeting for this date in pencil on the other side, plus title of the document; CD has signed "Mr. Darwin"; all else is in the hands of others.
  - To [?Henry DENNY]; Down (type 2), [ca. 1855-1861]; 120; ALS; 7 x4.5 4p.
    Thanks for answer to letter of 28 January; sorry corr. could not observe lice from domestic animals from distant lands; interested in aperea, had concluded that aperea was not progenitor of guinea pigs; does not know what corr. means by "stock-dove"; orders would probably be issued if corr. wrote to Council of Zoological Society, but corr. would have to visit the Gardens frequently to see that orders were carried out; still, corr. would get specimens this way; [Philip Lutley] Sclater would be interested in the birds.
    1. Type of Down address variant used was employed from 1843 to 1846 and from 1855 to 1861. CD did not know enough about pigeons in the earlier period to have written the highly technical treatment of the stock dove that is in this letter.
  - To [John Maurice] HERBERT; Down (type 2), [?1856] Jan. 2d. [wmk. 1855]; 121; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 4p.
    Thanks for book of poetry; "I shall keep to my dying day an unfading remembrance of the many pleasant hours (especially at Barmouth) 1 which we have spent together"; is permanently ill, so cannot visit; other family details.
    1. See: Life and Letters I, 165-66; and "Darwin's Journal," 6.
  - To [John] PHILLIPS; Down (type 2), [?1856] Jan. 18th; 122; ALS; 8 x5; 8p.
    Recommends reading of the discussion on cleavage and foliation in chapter VI of Darwin, South America (1846); skim page 140, but concluding remarks are on page 162; see also pages 144, 147, 157, 159, and 163, concerning confused cleavages and irregular strikes of foliation at crosses of geological series; cleavage distinct from stratification; "rocks which have been liquified by heat, sometimes have their crystallized materials so arranged, as almost to deserve to be called foliated..."; see also example in CD's description of the Falkland Islands, 1 pages 270-71; existence of grauwacke with clay-slates is perplexing, since clay-slate is apparently formed in deep and tranquil seas; could pressure which causes cleavage and movement along cleavage planes also break up rock, mingle varieties [of rocks] together "like fragments of ice in a glacier," and subsequently re-cement these fragments together; offers copies of the three volumes of Darwin, Geology of the Voyage of the Beagle. 2
    1. "On the Geology of the Falkland Islands," Q. Jl. geol. Soc. Lond., 2 (1846): 267-74.
    2. See also John Phillips, "Report on Cleavage and Foliation in Rocks, and on the Theoretical Explanations of these Phaenomena--Part I," Rep. Br. Ass. Advmt Sci., 26 (1856): pt. 1, 369-96.
  - To [Walter] ELLIOT; Down (type 2), 1856 Jan. 23.; 123; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Reminds Elliot of their acquaintance at [the B.A.A.S. meeting of 1855 in] Glasgow; wants some items which they discussed then, viz. measurements of differences in proportions of tigers, and remarks on domestic Pigeons "(& Poultry?)" which are extracted from "some work in an Eastern language"; will consult Ayin Akbaree 1 at the India House; is collecting domestic pigeons and poultry, wants Elliot to obtain a bird skinner to provide Indian skins of old, representative specimens of pigeons and poultry long bred in India, esp. tumblers and carriers; gives instructions for preparation of skins; apologies for imposition.
    1. Abu al-Fadhl ibn Mubarak, al-Hindi, Ayeen Akbery; or, The Institutes of the Emperor Akber, 2v., trans. from the original Persian by Francis Gladwin (London: J. Sewell, etc., 1800), esp. I, 270. See also Darwin, Variation under Domestication (1868), I, 205 and 205n.
  - To Mrs. [Katherine Murray Horner] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] Jan 26th [pmk. JA27/ 1856; wmk. 1855]; 124; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 7p. and env., add. [Mrs Lyell/ 14 Queens Road/ Gloucester Gate/ Regents Park/ London.]
    Printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: More Letters, I, 84-85 (letter 42). p. 85, line 11, illegible word is "rumour". At end of letter is: remembrances to husband, Colonel [Henry] Lyell.
  - To [George Henry Kendrick THWAITES]; Down (type 2), 1856 March 8th; 125; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Hopes Thwaites will publish his "facts on variation," esp. "particulars in regard to the species from different elevations, which show different degrees of capacity for cultivation at a new level"; [Joseph Dalton] Hooker has published a similar case with Himalaya rhododendrons; 1 regarding distribution of alpine plants, is there anything new concerning comparison between vegetation at the greater heights in Ceylon and alpine vegetation in the Himalaya, Neilgherries [i.e. Nilgiris, in southern India], or other maountains; do introduced and recently naturalized plants vary much in Ceylon; "The course of my work makes me more & more sceptical on the eternal immutability of species; yet the difficulties on the other theory of common descent seems to me frightfully great. In my work, which I shall not publish for 2 or 3 or perhaps more years; it is my intention to give, as far as I can & that will be very imperfectly, all the arguments & facts on both sides of the case, stating which side seems to me to preponderate."; wants pigeon skins from Ceylon; prefers to work carefully at varieties of a few animals than to compile brief notices on all domestic breeds; "I have now all English breeds of Pigeons alive, & am carefully observing them, making skeletons & crossing them."; wants ducks, rabbits, and poultry; Dr. [Edward Frederick] Kelaert [i.e. Kelaart] will help with poultry; apologies for imposition, "when a beggar once begins to beg he never knows when to stop!"
    1. "On the Climate and Vegetation of the Temperate and Cold Regions of East Nepal and the Sikkim Himalaya Mountains," Jl R. hort. Soc., 7 (1852): 69-131. See also Darwin, Origin (1859), 140.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] April 21st; 126; ALS; 6p. @ 8 x5, 2p. @ 3 1/4 x8; 8p., 3 sketches
    Lyell's case of lava beds passing into vertical columns is most perplexing, but is a "very important & extraordinary fact," and, as Lyell states, is a strong argument against "upheavement" as a cause of an angle of, say, twelve degrees, since lava columns could not have been formed at an inclination and then shifted to the vertical; lava must still have been moving downward when shrinkage produced columns; ask [William] Hopkins on this; thinks Hopkins or [Edward] Forbes has published a sketch of this phenomenon; has seen lava columns; suspects a similar process in glaciers; Lyell's Madeira expedition [in late 1853] was interesting.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] May 3d.; 127; ALS; 8 x5; 6p.
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 67-68. At beginning of letter is: thanks for letter; wishes Lyell had discussed further the lava columns [see previous letter, above]; has kept list of land shells, has made corrections, and is surprised by Lyell's knowledge; will borrow [Oswald] Heer, [ ?Ueber die Haus-Ameise Madeira's (Zürich: n.p., 1852)] while Lyell is abroad; Lyell's cases of transportal "beat all that I have ever heard...& if any body had put such cases hypothetically I shd have laughed at them"; Colymbetes [water beetle] flew on board Beagle 45 miles from land, which surprised [Thomas Vernon] Wollaston; Wollaston and others were at Down; "Wollaston strikes me as quite a first-rate man & very nice & pleasant into the bargain. It is really striking (but almost laughable to me) to notice the change in [Joseph Dalton] Hooker's & [Thomas Henry] Huxley's opinions on species during the last few years."
  - To Dr. [Henry Ambrose] OLDFIELD; Down (type 2), [1856] May 10th [end. Ansd. May 15.56; pmk. MY11/ 1856]; 128; ALS; 8 x5; 4p. and env., add. [Dr. Oldfield/ 8 Gloucester Gardens/ Gloucester Terrace/ Hyde Park/ London.--], end. [Ansd. May 15.56.]
    [William Sandys Wright] Waux referred CD to Oldfield because Oldfield once remarked that dogs represented in Assyrian drawings were like the Thibetan [i.e. Tibetan] dogs familiar to Oldfield in Nepaul [i.e. Nepal]; as CD is interested in ancient history of domesticated animals, does Oldfield think this resemblance close; describes resemblances and differences suspected; wants data on other breeds of dogs, poultry, fancy pigeons, and rabbits in Nepal; is collecting pigeons from all over world.
  - To [Samuel Pickworth WOODWARD]; Down (type 2), [1856]; 129; ALS; 8 x5; 2p.
    Has just finished [Woodward's] book, 2 has derived "much solid instruction & interest" from it; has written down some questions which he will ask in person when in London in about a fortnight.
    1. See Life and Letters II, 73.
    2. A Manual of the Mollusca; or, Rudimentary Treatise of Recent and Fossil Shells (London: J. Weale, 1851-1856). Published in three parts, in 1851, 1853, and 1856; issued thereafter as a single volume.
  - To [William Darwin] FOX; Down (type 2), [?1856] June 4th; 130; ALS; 8 x5; 2p. 1
    Thanks for "a Forking Cock, more like an ostrich than a simple fowl".
    1. On same sheet is a two-page letter from Mrs. Fox to her husband.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down, [1856 June] 16th; 131; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters II, 72. At end of letter is: "When you go abroad you are to lend me [?Philip Barker] Webb. & [Oswald] Heer, & can you add [Matthew Fontaine] Maury [the elder] ocean chart; [Samuel Pickworth] Woodward had it some time ago.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] Jun 25th. [end. 25 June. 1856]; 132; Partially ALS and partially LS; 13 x8.25 5p. and env., end. [(119)/ C. Darwin/ 25 June. 1856/ On reasons for doubting the/ Atlantis/ & continental extension theory/ in the Recent Period.]
    Printed in full, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 74-78. p. 76, line 4, questionable word is "Silla". p. 76, line 23, add "are" after "such". p. 77, line 4, change "Lowe" to "Low". p. 77, line 12, pluralize "formation".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] July 5th [end. July 5, 1856]; 133; Partially ALS and partially LS; 13 x8.25 3p. and fragment of env., end. [C. Darwin/ July 5, 1856/ Continental Extension./ Volcanos whether in/ areas of elevation or/ of subsidence.]
    First portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: More Letters, II, 135-37 (letter 489). p. 135, line 12, questionable word is "extensions". p. 136, line 31, add: local volcanic subsidence caused by shrinking of great volcanic piles is supported by frequent coincidence of volcanic tertiary streams and lakes or fresh water beds. At end of this portion is: CD's vague ideas on this subject are worthless; CD's ideas are not dogmatic.
    Next portion printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 71. At end of this portion is: shall not attempt to write a history of the subject, but did mention Lyell's Principles [ of Geology..., 3v. (London: John Murray, 1830-1833)]; will want Lyell to look over what CD will write about the Principles.
  - To Charles LYELL; Down (type 2), [1856] July 8th [end. July 8, 1856.]; 134; ALS; 8 x5; 8p. and env., add. [Sir Charles Lyell/ 53. Harley St/ London.], end. [C. Darwin/ continental extensions/ July 8. 1856.]
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 427-28 (letter 327). Small portion also printed in Life and Letters II, 78.
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 3), [?1856] Augt 21st; 135; ALS; 8 x5; 4p.
    Has been reading Eyton on pigs ["Some Osteological Peculiarities in Different Skeletons of the Genus Sus"], Proc. zool. Soc. Lond., [ 5 (1837): 23]; are offspring of cross between African and common pigs fertile; if Eyton does not know answer, ask Lord [Rowland] Hill; were Hill's African pigs domesticated; from where in Africa do they come; has pigeon skeletons for "every breed alive", but has not compared them yet; will need Eyton's help when he does; is compiling "Book on Variation" [i.e. Darwin, "Natural Selection"], but finds it slow work; family details.
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 2), [?1856 August] 27th; 136; ALS; 8 x5; 2p.
    Excuse this additional note; thinks Eyton has studied Herefordshire cattle; 1 believes there are two strains of this breed that can be distinguished by color on face; are there other distinguishing characters besides color?
    1. Eyton, The Herd Book of Hereford Cattle, 2v. (London: Longman and Co., 1846-1853).
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 2), [?1856] Aug. 31st; 137; ALS; 8 x5; 10p.
    Thanks for note and promise of more information on pigs; is collecting pig jaws to test [Johann Matthaus] Bechstein's assertion that number of incisors varies greatly in domestic pigs; can Eyton confirm this; approves of illustrations in Eyton's "Stud Book" [i.e. The Herd Book of Hereford Cattle; see previous letter, above], returns plates with thanks; after Writing, found source of his ideas, viz. Q. Rev., 1849, page 392, mentioning split in Herefordshire breed; 1 would like to mention this in [Darwin, "Natural Selection"] as a rare instance of the documentation of the origin of "even a sub-breed of a sub-breed"; will also refer to Eyton; comments on Eyton's birds; will quote Eyton's case of geese; 2 did Eyton breed the "grandchildren geese"; has been inquiring in India on same subject; one of most troublesome problems is distribution mechanism for species on distant islands; has tried resistance of seeds in sea water; check to see if dirt sticks to feet of birds; 3 check possibility of seed dispersion through pellets thrown up by owls or hawks; send contents of stomachs of dace and other white fish eaten by birds, so that CD can sow seeds contained therein; if Eyton collects cat skeletons, C[harles] Lyell has an odd Persien carcass and CD knows of another odd specimen; "I have put your words, that you like hearing from old naturalist friends, to a severe test."
    1. CD here refers to an enonymous review of Henry Stephens, The Book of the Farm..., 2nd ed., 2v. (Edinburgh and London: W. Blackwood and Sons, 1849), to be found in Q. Rev., 84 (1848-1849): 389-424.
    2. Eyton, "Remarks on the Skeletons of the Common Tame Goose, the Chinese Goose, and the Hybrid between the Two," Mag. nat. Hist., 4 (1840): 90-92.
    3. See Darwin, Origin (1859), 358-63ff; and Peckham, Variorum Origin, 575-79.